<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Usurpation defeated, and David restored being an exact parallel between David and our most Gracious Soveraign King Charls II. In their dangerous dissettlement, and wonderfull restauration. Laid open in a sermon on II Sam. XIX. 14. Preached on the publique solemn day of thanksgiving, May 24 1660 in the Collegiate Church of Manchester in the county palatine of Lancaster. By Henry Newcome Master in Arts, and minister of the Gospel there.</title>
            <author>Newcome, Henry, 1627-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829473</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829473</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33913</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53080)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33913)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1994:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Usurpation defeated, and David restored being an exact parallel between David and our most Gracious Soveraign King Charls II. In their dangerous dissettlement, and wonderfull restauration. Laid open in a sermon on II Sam. XIX. 14. Preached on the publique solemn day of thanksgiving, May 24 1660 in the Collegiate Church of Manchester in the county palatine of Lancaster. By Henry Newcome Master in Arts, and minister of the Gospel there.</title>
                  <author>Newcome, Henry, 1627-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Ralph Shelmerdine book-seller in Manchester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams's Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, XIX, 14 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:1"/>
            <p> Uſurpation Defeated, AND David Reſtored: Being an Exact Parallel between DAVID And our moſt Gracious Soveraign King Charls II. In their dangerous Diſſettlement, and wonderfull Reſtauration. Laid open in a SERMON on II SAM. XIX. 14. PREACHED On the Publique Solemn Day of Thankſgiving, <hi>MAY</hi> 24. 1660 in the Collegiate Church of
<hi>Mancheſter</hi> in the County Palatine of <hi>LANCASTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY NEWCOME</hi> Maſter in Arts, and Miniſter of the Goſpel there.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 24 21.</bibl>
               <p>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Shelmerdine</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:2"/>
            <head>To the HONOURABLE Sir <hi>GEORGE BOOTH,</hi> BARONET, one of the Members of the Honourable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS;</hi> The RIGHT WORSHIPFULL Sir <hi>RALPH ASHTON</hi> of <hi>Middleton,</hi> Knight &amp; Baronet, And the RIGHT WORSHIPFULL <hi>RICHARD HOLLAND</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Renowned Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon, preached ſome Moneths ſince, and at the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of many Friends, now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed;<pb facs="tcp:33913:3"/>which hath gotten of all this time of its ſuſpenſion, and intended utter ſuppreſſion, no higher an eſteem with its unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Author, had need when forced out, to ſeek for Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage: Neither are there any to whom I could more willingly and confidently engage my ſelf for ſuch a favour then your ſelves; whom I have cauſe to preferre in my thoughts, not only for your undeſerved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects upon occaſion to my ſelf, (which I would hereby with all thankfulneſſe acknowledge) but alſo for the Renowned Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, Hazards and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings you have undergone for the Publique. It is gratefull to me, that I ſhould by the Providence of God, Date this<pb facs="tcp:33913:3"/>Epiſtle to ſuch a Sermon in this Moneth, which but a year ſince was the ſeaſon of ſo many hazards, and dreadfully threatning Dangers, to your ſelves principally, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others with this poor Town of <hi>MANCHESTER,</hi> which ſo <hi>willingly offered themſelves</hi> with you in that <hi>Cauſe of GOD</hi> you ſo ſignally engaged in: Shall it ever be forgotten by us, what the Lord hath wrought? May not that holy Providence and Power of his be for ever adored, that hath in ſuch a ſhort time turned for us <hi>our Mourning into Rejoycing?</hi> That thoſe proud Waves ſhould be ſo ſoon and remarkably bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon us, and be now <hi>like waters that are paſſed away.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33913:4"/>I hope the profit of theſe Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Deliverances ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with us, as a ſufficient and laſting ground of engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon our hearts to fear, ſerve, truſt and delight in that God who hath thus wrought for us.</p>
            <p>And if this poor ſervice may any way tend to the recording and perpetuating of our ſenſe of this wonderfull Mercy, and of our faithfull and loyal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging for, and rejoycing in the glorious Return of his Gracious Majeſty to theſe Nations (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the People of theſe Two Counties engaging with you as their faithfull and active Leaders have cauſe to conceive they have a double ſhare) I have the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt I could aim at in this ſo<pb facs="tcp:33913:4"/>deſpicable an undertaking. And humbly craving pardon for this boldneſs, I commit you to the bleſſing of <hi>that God that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth all things for us:</hi> And am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unfaignedly affectionate And unworthyeſt Servant In the GOSPEL, <hi>Henry Newcome.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Mancheſter,</hi>
                  <date>Aug. 29. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:5"/>
            <head>TO THE Reverend, his Worthy Friend, Mr. <hi>HENRY NEWCOME,</hi> Miniſter of CHRIST at <hi>MANCHESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>REVEREND SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Nce more by eſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence I have had a view of another Sermon of yours. In the former you opened a Dore of Hope for Sinners meeting with their God, and in this you have opened another Dore for Subjects meeting with their Soveraign. The diſtance betwixt God and Sinners was great; Heaven and Hell are oppoſite, and <hi>between them there is a great gulf fixed.</hi> And how powerfully did you make appear that the Gulf might be<pb facs="tcp:33913:6"/>ſhot, that Heaven and Earth might meet; that God and Sinners might be reconciled:
<note place="margin">Ezr. 10 2.</note> 
               <hi>Yet now there is hope in Iſrael concerning this thing.</hi> The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance likewiſe between our Soveraign and his Subjects was very great: True Soveraignty is from Heaven,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that be are ordained of God:</hi> But Rebellion and Treaſon are from Hell, they are
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.23.</note> 
               <hi>as the Sin of Witchcraft,</hi> which is ordered and ordained by the Devil; and betwixt theſe there was a great Gulf or Sea, for one Land could not bear them both: And yet how ably have you made it appear, That Seas might be croſſed, That the Powers from above, and Treaſons from the deep might peaceably meet, That his Majeſty and Subjects might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled. It was not impoſſible with God to <hi>bow the hearts of all the men of</hi> England, <hi>even as the heart of one men, ſo that they ſhould ſend this word unto the King, Return thou and all thy Servants.</hi> Me thinks I look upon theſe two Sermons as two Twins, which though they came not out together in<pb facs="tcp:33913:6"/>one day, yet they were conceived in one Womb, and they made haſte one after the other: And now being come to light they reſemble each other both in matter and form: As the two Tables were both of Stone, and were both hewed by <hi>Moſes</hi> at Gods appointment, and in the one of them is written our Duty to God, and in the other our Duty to our Neighbour; ſo are theſe two Sermons for their matter as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, and for their form, hewed out by your ſelf, by Gods own order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and in the one of them is written our eſpecial Duty to God, pointed out in the firſt Commandement of the firſt Table; and in the other is our Duty to Man,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>our Head, our King, our Supream,</hi> pointed out in the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſecond Table,
<note place="margin">Eph. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>which is the firſt Commandement with Promiſe.</hi> Were it not pity that any man ſhould put aſunder thoſe things which God hath joyned together? You have taught us comfortably to <hi>hope in God,</hi> and ſhall we be deprived of that ſecond Leſſon, <hi>To honour the King?</hi> What<pb facs="tcp:33913:7"/>if this Table hath been by ſome as broken and laid aſide? the Lord hath put it into your heart to hew it again, and by his aſſiſtance you have fairly written the
<hi>words of the Covenant:</hi> My humble advice is, that ſuch a Talent may not be hid and buryed in the Earth; but as you have Preached it, ſo you would pleaſe to Print it, and make it yet more legible to all the World. You may think it is now out of Date, his Majeſty who was invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Return is now Returned: And what then?</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was one of the moſt ſeaſonable Sermons that ever I read; it was <hi>a Word fitly ſpoken:</hi> And I ſhould look upon that Book as an Ornament in my Study, which I might call
<note place="margin">Prov. 25.11.</note> 
               <hi>Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver.</hi> But</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is of conſtant and continual uſe. As the words in the Text were only in ſeaſon when <hi>David</hi> lived, and when that Negotiation was tranſacted; yet to this day (as now we ſee) is that Scripture
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction<pb facs="tcp:33913:7"/>in Righteouſneſſe.</hi> So will this Sermon be till the Worlds end. From this one Doctrine of Loyalty, all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may be for ever rightly informed in Judgement and inſtructed in Life: Or if any hereafter ſhould be diſloyal (which God forbid) it would be for Reproof of the Weak, and for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Wicked.</p>
            <p>Our Nations have been a long time under great reproach, let this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon witneſs to the World, <hi>That the Lord hath rolled our reproach away,</hi> in that he hath wrought us into the temper of his Darling <hi>Judah, Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all our hearts, even as the heart of one man,</hi> to become truely Loyal. God dealt thus with <hi>Judah,</hi> but he hath dealt more graciouſly with us; for it was but <hi>the heart of all the men of Judah;</hi> or if
<hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> had both been joyned, they had been the hearts of only One Nation, and no more: But with us God hath done more wonderfully, in that he hath bowed the hearts of Two Nations, Three Nations, all at once, as if Three<pb facs="tcp:33913:8"/>Nations had but one heart. And at his Majeſties Return, ſuch Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings were on all hands as never
<hi>England</hi> ſaw before. The King in his Proclamation is pleaſed to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, That both his Royal heart, and the hearts of his People, were as full of mutual love, and confidence, and joy, as became ſuch a Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of King and People. Now Sir, let this be writ in Marble:
<note place="margin">Job 19.23,24.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that they were Printed in a Book, that they were graven with an Iron Pen, and laid in the Rock for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Records may laſt long, yet time may injure them, but theſe words with <hi>Job</hi> I would have laſt for ever: <hi>That King and Subjects, kept at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance by Uſurped Powers for about Twelve years, yet then met together with ſuch love, and confidence, and joy, yea with ſuch teſtimonies of love, and confidence, and joy, in Bonefires, Bells, Trumpets, Thunderings of Shot and ſinging of Prayſes, as if Heaven and Earth had met.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33913:8"/>Before this we were the reproach of Nations indeed, but now tell me <hi>France, Italy, Spain, Germany,</hi> or any other Countrey; if ever was the like day in any of your Nations. Surely <hi>this was the Lords doing, and it was, and is, and for ever will be marvellous in our eyes.</hi> The Lord bleſs theſe Papers, and all your labour to the good of his Church: So prayes</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unworthy Brother In the work of the Miniſtery,
<hi>Iſaac Ambroſe.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Gacſlang,</hi>
                  <date>Aug. 21. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33913:9"/>
            <head>Vſurpation Defeated, AND DAVID RESTORED.
<q>
                  <bibl>II SAM. 19. 14.</bibl>
                  <p>And he bowed the heart of all the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> even as the heart of one man, ſo that they ſent this word unto the King, Return thou and all thy Servants.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>verſ.</hi> is a part of the very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Hiſtory of <hi>Davids</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his Kingdom, after the Rebellion and Uſurpation of his ambitious Son <hi>Abſalom.</hi> It is eaſie to ſee the ſcope of the ſtory in reviewing the<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33913:10"/>Context. After the death of
<hi>Abſalom,</hi> the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſpeak of fetching the King back, as it is <hi>verſ.</hi> the 9. and 10. of this chap.
<hi>David</hi> ſends to the houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> a <hi>Meſſage</hi> and <hi>Declaration,</hi> to be delivered by <hi>Zadok</hi> and
<hi>Abiathar</hi> to the Elders of <hi>Judah, v.</hi> 11, 12. another to
<hi>Amaſa,</hi> the <hi>General</hi> of <hi>Abſaloms</hi> Army, <hi>v.</hi>
13. the effect of which <hi>Meſſage</hi> and <hi>Declaration</hi> you have in the words of the Text, which is two-fold.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The univerſal and cordial inclination of the people towards the King, in theſe words, <hi>And he bowed the heart of all the men of Judah, even as the heart of one man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Loyal Meſſage and invitation they ſent to him, of returning to his Kingdom and Royal City, in theſe words, <hi>So they ſent this word to the King, Return thou, and all thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>We ſhall briefly explain the words, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you will ſtill more clearly diſcern their Emphaſis, and their ſuteableneſs to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>And <hi>he, he</hi> bowed. This relative is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured to refer to divers antecedents.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>He;</hi> Some will have it to be <hi>David, he,</hi> that is <hi>David</hi> by his <hi>gracious Meſſage and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of his tenderneſs to his people, and readineſs to forgive, to pardon
<hi>Amaſa,</hi> and to prefer him upon his ſubmiſſion, did hugely ſway with the Elders of <hi>Judah,</hi> and with all the people, that forthwith they ſent unto him.</item>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33913:10"/>
               <item>2. <hi>He,</hi> ſome will have it to be <hi>Zadok</hi> or
<hi>Abiathar,</hi> to whom the Meſſage was ſent: they were of the Prieſts of the Lord, had intereſt in the Elders and People too, and appearing ſatisfied in the Kings meſſage, they bowed the people to this unanimous and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull complyance. God hath oft made uſe of his ſervants in the Miniſtry, in furthering ſuch works as theſe are by them.</item>
               <item>3. Some will have him to be <hi>Amaſa.</hi> Indeed he is the immediate antecedent, the meſſage to him is in the next verſe before. The King offering him ſo fairly, and he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the power of the Sword, commanding the people in Arms, and now returning to his <hi>loyalty</hi> and
<hi>obedience,</hi> he had influence upon all the people hereby, towards their inviting in the King again. God often hath made great changes in Nations by the change of the Generals heart. Thus <hi>Abner</hi> brought back
<hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>David</hi> before,
<note place="margin">2 Sam.</note> and <hi>Amaſa</hi> might do it now. Whether <hi>David</hi> is the <hi>he,</hi> or the Prieſt, or the General, whether King or <hi>Zadok</hi> or <hi>Amaſa,</hi> is not material, any of them might be inſtrumental. And all have been ſo in our caſe to the like purpoſe. But we muſt ſay,</item>
               <item>4. This <hi>he</hi> may be God, and it muſt be ſo, if we underſtand a principal efficient by it. <hi>God bowed the heart of the men of Judah,</hi> none could do it but he, who hath the heart of all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33913:11"/>men in his hand. And though <hi>Davids</hi> meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage might do much, and <hi>Zadoks</hi> faithfull ſpeech much, and the Elders compliance with the King, might have influence upon the people, and
<hi>Amaſa</hi> with the Sword in his hand might do more in this buſineſs; yet God did work by them all, and was the chief Doer. Whether he be primarily meant in the Text or no, yet he is neceſſarily and chiefly to be implyed and underſtood in the buſineſs. It is the great work of the Lord, whoever are inſtruments in it, by what means ſoever it is brought to paſs, that the heart of the people is thus bowed, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>He <hi>bowed.</hi>] This word implyes two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That there had been a contrary tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the heart of the people: It was averſe enough unto <hi>David.</hi> It did ſtand deſperately oppoſite and ſtiffe and hardned toward him, yet now it is
<hi>bowed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. That there is now a compliance wrought, which yet was not of it ſelf, but brought upon it by means. It was <hi>bowed.</hi> It did not yield it ſelf of it ſelf, but was taken hold of as it were, and brought down to a compliance by ſtrong hand, It was of refractary and exceeding oppoſite made as compliant as could be expected or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33913:11"/>The <hi>heart.</hi>] It is not ſaid the
<hi>hearts</hi> of all the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> in the plural number, but
<hi>heart</hi> in the ſingular, to denote, That oft there is a general ſpirit prevails upon the people of a Land, they are one body, and ſometimes poſſeſſed with one ſoul: there is the temper of a Man and the temper of the Nation to be ſeen; and ſometimes it is for good, and ſometimes for evil, and this to be diſtinguiſhed, when the Chief of a Nation are bent ſuch a way, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>love to have it ſo.</hi> The heart of the people, the temper and ſpirit of the Nation are ſet the right way now to reſtore <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all the men of <hi>Judah, even as the heart of one man.</hi>] They were univerſally enclined, unanimous in the Vote, <hi>all</hi> concurred to a man, or they were as eaſily prevailed with, as if but one man had been to be dealt with. Sometimes we ſay, For one or two we can deal with, but a multitude it is hard to know how to turn it; but God can ſway a multitude as well as one ſingle man. They were bowed as the <hi>heart of one man,</hi> a moſt cordial unanimous concurrence is hereby expreſſed. For the meſſage they ſent, it may be preſumed it was ſent by <hi>Honourable Commiſſioners</hi> and <hi>Delegates</hi> from the <hi>Elders</hi> of
<hi>Judah,</hi> and the Generall. They reſolve to have the King fetcht back, and they ſend<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33913:12"/>to him, to deſire him ſpeedily to return,
<hi>and all his ſervants.</hi> The King was glad to flee from
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to ſave his life, and ſome <hi>Shimei's</hi> fearfully abuſed him in the way; but now they ſend for him back again with much honour and affection to him as their rightfull <hi>Lord</hi> and
<hi>Soveraign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thing that preſents it ſelf from this ſubject to our meditation, as exceeding ſuitable to our preſent occaſion, is, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and wonderfulneſs of this change in this hearty and unanimous vote and meſſage for the bringing the King back to his Throne and Royal City, after he had been ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanely, diſloyally, and treacherouſly dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out as he had been.</p>
            <p>We may conſider ſeveral things in this caſe of
<hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> which may run parallel to our preſent buſineſs. Take it in two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Conſider, the diſſettlement and almoſt deſpair that <hi>Davids</hi> affairs were in.</item>
               <item>2. The manner and nature of his reſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In both which you may obſerve things wonderfull, and with greateſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to be acknowledged, and the like in our preſent occaſion.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The diſſettlement and almoſt deſpair that
<hi>Davids</hi> affairs were in. You cannot prize the deliverance, unleſs you take a full view of the danger you are eſcaped from.<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33913:12"/>Conſider <hi>Davids</hi> ſad condition of affairs,
<list>
                  <item>1. In the deſign that was layd againſt him.</item>
                  <item>2. In the pretexts to uſher it in.</item>
                  <item>3. In the manner of its mannagement.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The deſign that was layd againſt the King.</hi> It was <hi>Abſalom</hi> aſpired, he aimed to be King in his Fathers ſtead. The deſign was to exclude the rightfull Governour from his Royalty, and to place this ambitious Prince in his ſtead: and for this end he raiſes war, draws many into a confederacy, they plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to deſtroy the King, to ſecure the Uſurper in the Throne: This was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; a moſt wicked and unnatural attempt. Any thing ſometimes is adventured upon. <hi>Regnandi cauſà: occidar modo imperet,</hi> Let me die, ſaid proud
<hi>Agrippina,</hi> ſo be it her ſon <hi>Nero</hi> might reign: Men will adventure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, religion, life, nay ſoul and all, to get into rule and dominion. This was the deſign in the ſtory, and no leſs hath been more then <hi>deſigned</hi> in our dayes. <hi>Abſalom</hi> might in time have had a good title to the Crown, but it was rebellion in the Heir of the Crown to be more then a <hi>Servant,</hi> whileſt his Father lived: Much more then moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred Treaſon in Subjects, ſome of them of the vileſt and meaneſt, to ſupplant the King, as they did, to Uſurp the Throne.
<hi>They</hi> aimed to kill the King, <hi>ours</hi> effected it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33913:13"/>a moſt wretched and unparallel'd act, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by the ſobereſt in the Nation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Murther,</hi> and now declared and owned to be ſuch in all mens mouths. It was not of Son againſt the Father; but of wicked men againſt Father and Son too. The deſign againſt the late King was like that of <hi>Ahab</hi> againſt <hi>Naboth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>To kill and alſo to take poſſeſſion;</hi> and to his preſent Majeſty it was like that of the unrighteous Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, that ſaid,
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.38.</note> 
               <hi>This is the Heir, come let us kill him, and the Inheritance ſhall be ours.</hi> This was the deſign.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The pretext it was uſhered in with. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaloms</hi> Treaſon was brought in with very ſpecious pretences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Of publique good, and redreſſe of Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Abſalom</hi> knew the peoples grievances, and made them full as many as they felt them to be. Chap. 15.2,3. <hi>Thy matters are good, but none is deputed of the King to hear them.</hi> None appointed to do juſtice, and therefore,
<hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>O that I were made a Judge!</hi> And then I would ſee matters better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. The people were prepoſſeſſed with
<hi>Abſaloms</hi> great good will to the Subject. Oh! he is tender of our Liberties, and therefore queſtionleſſe, if he riſe, ſay the deceived people, our beſt friend is up, and it ſtands us all in hand to ſtand by him, that<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33913:13"/>ſtands ſo for the good of the Publique. While all this pretext of publique good is but in Engliſh, <hi>The liberty of the Subject.</hi> There is a Liberty which is our Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and might have been maintained without violation to the Lawes of God and Man, but this was the bait that many were enſnared by. Oh the noiſe that hath been for the Publique, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice, the ſecurity of the good people of theſe Nations! this hath been cryed up to be the <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> And the Government ſetled by the Fundamental Lawes of this Land, and ſworn unto by us, muſt be changed for the publique good; when it is clear as the Noon Sun, that private deſigns and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts are ſought and carryed on under theſe pretexts. We talk of publique eaſe and liberty of the people, and of our <hi>Keepers of the Liberties;</hi> whereas the peoples Taxes and burthens encreaſe all along under this way of Government, and muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do ſo, to keep it up: And theſe <hi>Keepers</hi> apparently encreaſe themſelves, and to keep their unjuſt acquirements, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Settlement muſt be kept up over the whole Nations. The naked truth now appears, to ſet up an <hi>Abſalom</hi> in the Throne is the deſign, under the pretenſe of Juſtice he will do to the people. So we are neceſſitated to keep up the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33913:14"/>of a <hi>Free State,</hi> as they call it, to preſerve the Eſtates of a few men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly gotten, which cannot endure the teſt of a righteous ſettlement to the true <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> good of the Nation. This is the firſt pretext.</p>
            <p n="2">The Second Pretext is of <hi>piety and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> whereby this deſperate ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is introduced, chap. 15.7,8. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires leave of his Father, that he may go <hi>to perform his Vow in Hebron,</hi> a religious ſervice, and piece of Gods Worſhip, then in uſe, wherein by ſacrifice they engaged themſelves to God, &amp;c. And he further relates the ground of it to be, the deep ſence that he had of the Lords deliverance of him in his former troubles, that then he promiſed <hi>to ſerve the Lord:</hi> So that it is not only the pretext of a meer Vow, for that time, or of ſo much Religion only, as might be expreſſed in what accompanyed a Vow, but he would make this <hi>Vow,</hi> not only a part of his intended religiouſneſs towards God, but an Introduction into a more ſtrict courſe then heretofore: He would thus begin, and henceforward be very ſtrict and ſerious in the Lords ſervice. And now how much might this take with the people? not only to get them into his Conſpiracy, but to tye them to him, when they were in. They might a little ſtartle,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33913:14"/>when they heard him declare to Uſurp the Kingdome: but then this would ſway much with the people: <hi>He is known to be a great Favourer of the publique Liberty, and a man that we ſee owns the ſervice of God, and ſets out Religiouſly, and therefore we may the better ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with him:</hi> He doth not declare againſt the Temple; not threaten to caſt off the true God, and to introduce Idolatry, but in his very entrance into his work, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends more then ordinary piety and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is eaſie in our parallel to finde out an <hi>Abſalom,</hi> that had a deſign to aſpire, that never ſhewed much Religion, till it would advance a wicked deſign: On the ſuddain he is religious, the only popular man, all for devotion and the Lords ſervice: Oh! ſay the poor people, this cannot be murther, and rebellion, and uſurpation, and perjury, that ſuch men as theſe are enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in. They are not prophane, notorious ſenſual men, but men of the greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, of the ſtricteſt life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>In nomine Domini incipit omne malum.</hi>
               </q> A Proverbial ſpeech firſt taken up from the Popes Murtherous Bulls and Edicts that uſed to come out thus in Chriſts name. It hath been one of the deſigns of the Devil ſince the Church was Chriſtian, to bring in his greateſt perſecutions under the diſguiſe of<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33913:15"/>ſome great profeſſion; the matter elſe would want Complices to carry it on. A vile man in eſteem with a good deſign would have a few followers, and a ſeeming good man hath a great advantage in his hand of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying many to a bad buſineſs, if he dare lead in it. Men are too apt to follow men, and can hardly keep out of Errour, if a tolerable perſon undertake their conduct. It is hard for the vulgar to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good men and bad actions, as if it muſt ceaſe to be evil when ſuch men dare engage in it: Whereas men ſhould judge men by their actions, and not actions by men. Oh! what pretenſes of Religion and godlineſs hath there been in the late miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, that have been perpetrated? calling upon God; appealing unto God to decide the controverſie, nay perpetrating villany upon impulſes pretended from the Spirit of God, ſecurity of Religion, liberty for ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This hath been cryed up, as their <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> that had the blood of Kings and Prophets at the bottom of it, like that Mic. 2.10,11. <hi>They build up Sion with blood, and Jeruſalem with iniquity—yet will they lean upon the Lord, and ſay, Is not the Lord among us? none evil can come upon us?</hi> Nay, their unheard of villanies are made the fulfilling of their Vows: no return for their deliverances and victories ſo proper, as to raſe our Foundations, murther our King,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33913:15"/>pull down the Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as no doubt it was in deſign, yet all along to advance Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion too. None ſo cruel among the <hi>Turks</hi> as a Renegado Chriſtian; and ſo none more like to ruine Religion then the Apoſtate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, and much the more if in truth an Apoſtate and yet a Profeſſor ſtill. <hi>Abſalom</hi> we know not what a King he might have proved, he was never tryed, ours have had time enough to have ſhewed ſome of their great good, they ſeemed to be big with; but we never could ſee a reality in them to this end to this day. But thus we agree in this ſecond particular, in the introduction of the deſign, with high pretenſes of Religion and the Liberty of the people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The manner of the management, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of this deſign,</hi> ſeveral things are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in that.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Many drawn into the buſineſſe that meant well,</hi> the liker to be more reſolute in the undertaking.
<hi>Abſalom</hi> he knew what he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by his Vow, there were 200 followed him from <hi>Jeruſalem in the ſimplicity of their hearts,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.11. meant nothing leſs then treaſon or murther to their King and his Father, but when in the buſineſs cheated and drawn hoodwinkt into this deſign, help'd it forward. And ſo all over <hi>Iſrael</hi> he had his Agents, who were privy to his deſign, and they at the ſign given drew in the people in like manner. Many a time deſperate<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33913:16"/>buſineſſes are carried on under other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, upon the ſecret deſign of a few. A ſad unnatural civil War is kindled, is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on a great way, too far, if it had been the will of God; parties engaged declare themſelves defenſive, they proteſt, and vow, and Covenant they had no deſign againſt his Majeſties <hi>Royal perſon,</hi> or
<hi>juſt honour and greatneſſe.</hi> The buſineſs goes on, the victory falls to their ſide. Now the <hi>Abſaloms</hi> appear, and they ſhew what their deſign was: The people went <hi>in their ſimplicity,</hi> meaning no other then what was declared to them, which hath ſufficiently appeared in that the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs could not be effected till force was put upon the Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Lords clearly diſmiſſed, near 300 Commoners pull'd out, and kept out of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; many hundreds in the Nation would never ſay a <hi>Confederacy with them,</hi> and have ſuffered according to their firſt declared Principles and innocent intentions, upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion all along under theſe Uſurpations. But yet many were drawn in no doubt, <hi>in their ſimplicity,</hi> to go on further with them. If this had been known at firſt to have been the deſign, it might in all liklihood have been never advanced one ſtep: but they take their advantage, the common people, and ſome good people of midling capacities, others ſeduced and infected in their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, are gotten on further into the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33913:16"/>decoy'd and cheated into the deſign, to follow that curſed <hi>Abſalom</hi> to the Throne. They pretend it is the Parliaments cauſe ſtill, and the people generally make no great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a Parliament conſiſting of <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> treating with the <hi>King,</hi> and upon the matter agreed with him, and a bit of a Parliament, the <hi>Lords</hi> removed, and the beſt and greateſt number of the <hi>Commons</hi> forcibly ſecluded, and to deſtroy the
<hi>King</hi> too. Alas! many went in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and many in ſimplicity, meaning no hurt, not foreſeeing the guile, nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the treachery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There was a great multitude engaged in Abſaloms buſineſſe againſt David.</hi> The text ſayes <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>The conſpiracy was ſtrong.</hi> It was ſtrong,
<list>
                  <item>1 In that the whole body of the people were gotten into it.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>David</hi> the rightfull King was forced to flie from the Royal City, and to go over <hi>Jordan</hi> to ſave his life, and therefore the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters roſe very high againſt him. We need not apply this. It is evident the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were either conſenting, or forced ro ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in the Uſurpation. <hi>David</hi> gone over <hi>Jordan</hi> to eſcape for his life.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>There was cruel policy and craft to the height uſed in the buſineſſe. Abſaloms</hi> party was much ſtrengthened by
<hi>Achitophel</hi> the <hi>Gilonite</hi> joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the buſineſs, chap.
15. <hi>v.</hi> 12. Two<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33913:17"/>great things there were in
<hi>Achitophels</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, in that he was a man of ſuch vaſt abilities for Counſe: 2 Sam. 16.23. <hi>The Counſel of Achitophel, which he counſelled in thoſe dayes, was as if a man had enquired at the Oracle of God, ſo was all the Counſel of Achitophel both with David and with Abſalom:</hi> His counſel had ſuch authority in the Councel, it was ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, and this counſel was gotten to <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loms</hi> ſide.</p>
            <p n="2">Secondly, in that he had been <hi>Davids</hi> Counſellor, and ſo underſtood the affairs of the Nation, the <hi>Arcana Imperii;</hi> knew <hi>Davids</hi> way of counſel, and ſo could better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and prevent his reſtauration, and always give <hi>Abſalom</hi> the way into the ſtrength of the Nation by this his experience. This was a great blow to
<hi>David,</hi> and advantage to <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> Certainly the deſign here that was ſo ſtrong, was laid in deepeſt policy: We had a man that had <hi>Abſaloms</hi> pride and ambition, and <hi>Achitophels</hi> head-piece. Men laid their devices as low as Hell, (but that their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels were defeated by him, <hi>who taketh the crafty in their own craftineſſe, and whoſe counſels muſt ſtand</hi>) their policy was very formidable, and a great while ſucceſſefull. That there were thoſe that joyned what they could contribute to this work, that had been of his Majeſties own Servants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I need not here aſſert. There was wiſdome, treachery and utmoſt<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33913:17"/>ingratitude concentred to keep our
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> down.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly (to mention no more of this kinde)
<hi>Abſoloms deſign was ſecured in a deſperate peece of wickedneſs;</hi> and this was no ſmall ſtrength to his party and diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to <hi>David.</hi> The politick peece of wickedneſs was from this <hi>Achitophels</hi> counſel, and that is, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.20,21,22.
<hi>Abſolom</hi> muſt go in to his Fathers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines in the ſight of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> on the top of the houſe. And what would this do? why, ſayes he, <hi>Then all Iſrael ſhall hear that thou art abhorred of thy Father, then ſhall the hands of all that are with thee be ſtrong.</hi> How would this ſtrengthen the hands of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> with him? why, theſe two wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It would aſſure the people that <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> muſt ſtick <hi>to them,</hi> as well as they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured <hi>with him;</hi> for they might ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times doubt of the buſineſs, there may be myſteries between the Father, and the Son, and <hi>David</hi> recover a little ſtrength; why, <hi>Abſolom</hi> offended him once afore, and he got his favour again. The King may be tender to his Son upon his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion. It may prove but baniſhment, or keeping from Court a while, as it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the fault may then fall heavily upon many of us as Inſtigators, and Abetters of this raſh young man in his Enterprize,<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33913:18"/>and he may happen let us fall to the Kings mercy, in hope, of his Fathers pardon for any thing that yet is done. Therefore ſayes <hi>Achitophel,</hi> Do ſome odious thing that the people may be ſure of thee. Nay, may the people now ſay, We may venture with him; for he dares never leave us, when he hath ſo unnaturally defiled his Fathers bed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It will make the people firm to <hi>Abſolom</hi> by making them ſee, they can now no longer dally in the buſineſs. The cauſe is declared by this open villany of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> we are gotten in, we have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced him, have brought him to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and he hath now under our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and aſſiſtance perpetrated this villany. There is no hope of ever being pardoned either for him, or us, that are ſo far engaged with him, when ſuch a thing as this is done; who can hope the King ſhould forgive us, when we have provoked him on this manner! The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy was devilliſh to linke <hi>Abſolom</hi> and his Forces by ſuch a villany:
<hi>Themiſtocles</hi> would make a golden bridge for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to retreat upon at any time, count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it no wiſdome to force an enemy to fight whether he would or no. When there is no hope of mercy, men will ſell their lives as dear as they can. This was the deſign in <hi>Abſoloms</hi> caſe, to make
<hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33913:18"/>and his party deſperate, that hopes of Indempnity might never ſpoil their reſolution. He puts it paſt hopes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, that that might never make them indifferent in the undertaking, nor mar their valour. A device if one would rake hell for one, you cannot finde one more devilliſh, and yet ſerving to this deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate deſign. How muſt
<hi>David</hi> ever get over this, when his enemies are ſo united and engaged to ſtand againſt him? Ours was of the ſame brood, and from the ſame father (no doubt) the Devil that <hi>Achitophel</hi> fetcht this. To keep
<hi>David</hi> out, we murder the Kings Royal Father, and in a horrid manner. If ſome few Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinates had done it, they might have made them to have born the blame; but it is done in the ſight of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Sun, in the Kings Royal City, before his own Gates, in the crowd of his people, on purpoſe to make as many partakers of the thing as might be, that they might have the more Abetters to cleave to them now for very protection. Moſt of the great Officers are made Judges, that theſe might, to prevent the like Judgement, and ſentence on themſelves, ſtick together to the laſt man. Any thing but the Murther of his own Father, a King may upon principles of honour, and prudence par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. But here many engaged to be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33913:19"/>now againſt the Heir of the Crown, thoſe that were not Judges and Actors they have another device to get many of them engaged too; And that is by <hi>taking poſſeſsion</hi> as well as
<hi>Killing,</hi> and ſo by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Kings Lands for ſmall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, they raiſe money at preſent, but they do more to their deſign, they ſtrengthen their party unſpeakably thereby. There is now an intereſt in the Nation that muſt be reſpected under this very notion, which ſhews how there wanted not vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany to make their party ſtrong and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. Matters had in all likelihood never held ſo long as they have done, if men had not been choaked with <hi>Purchaſes.</hi> Many men ivolved in ſo much guilt, as that they have juſtly deſpaired of pardon, and many ſo deep in eſtates none of their own, as loath to think of reſtitution. And thus the
<hi>hand of the people is made ſtrong with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolom</hi> carried on his buſineſs but a while, and though it was notably laid, yet being unſettled, more eaſily brought down.
<hi>Aegrius ejicitur quam non admittitur hoſtis.</hi> But ours got ſettled, an Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of almoſt a dozen years ſtanding, the channel quite turned, Eſtates gotten and improved, and ſo men more loath to part with them. And therefore in this the danger and hazard of diſſettlement hath exceeded.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33913:19"/>But ſure <hi>Davids</hi> caſe (both
<hi>Davids</hi>) is very hazzardous and ſad, when ſuch a deſperate deſign laid, ſo uſhered in, ſo cruelly managed, raiſed upon the abuſed well-meaning of many, the crafty and treacherous counſels of others, the ſtrength of the multitudes, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of deſpair for ever receding from it, and yet this was that, and our <hi>Davids</hi> caſe.</p>
            <p n="2">Now ſecondly, Conſider <hi>the manner and nature of his Re-ſettlement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Davids</hi> Re-ſettlement, and our <hi>Davids</hi> Re-ſettlement: In both which you will finde things alike parallelly wonderful.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Conſider the manner how God hath brought it to paſs.</item>
               <item>2. Conſider the thing thus far effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider the manner how the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence hath brought <hi>David</hi> to his Kingdome again, when his affairs were ſo deſperate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Several, notwithſtanding this general defection, remained faithful to David.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral fled out of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.17,18. Many people when he fled went after him; his ſervants, the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethites, the Pelethites, the Gittites, &amp;c.</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on before him. <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> his
<hi>Kinſ-men</hi> and famous <hi>Generals,</hi> they found the part of the Kingdome beyond the<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33913:20"/>River, though inconſiderable to the body of the people, but two Tribes for ten, yet they were faithful to him; the Prieſts of the Lord <hi>abode with the Ark,</hi> yet <hi>Davids</hi> true friends, <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archite</hi> goes back, and by his counſel with <hi>Abſolom</hi> furthers and ſecures <hi>Davids</hi> affairs truly and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually. <hi>David</hi> was forced out of his City, and yet not out of the hearts and affections of all his Subjects. Several were true, loyal and conſtant to him, and this helped up his intereſt again. And ſo with us the Lord kept many hearts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to ſound and upright principles of Covenanted loyalty to his Majeſty. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral run the ſame fate of Exilement with him. The part of his Kingdome beyond the River true to him, gave him admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, were oppreſſed, and almoſt ruined for him. He had
<hi>Huſhaies</hi> that had a reſpect to his intereſt as there might be occaſion. There were thouſands in <hi>Iſrael</hi> that were faithful in Covenant, that never bowed <hi>their knee to Baal:</hi> that would never ſay,
<hi>A Confederacy with them, that ſaid a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy,</hi> that were true in their hearts to <hi>David,</hi> and ready to ſhew themſelves when ever God would begin to give a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving to his Majeſties juſt cauſe. Several whom the Lord kept upright in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that grieved to ſee the diſhonour done to Religion, and wrong to Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33913:20"/>and inferiours, and were ready In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in Gods hands to reſcue the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ruined rights of their King and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Fervent prayers were put up to God by</hi> David
<hi>and his party,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3. and other <hi>Pſalms</hi> 42. and 43. were penned upon this occaſion. But eſpecially <hi>David</hi> moſt earneſtly puts in a Caveat at the Throne of Grace againſt
<hi>Achitophel,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.31. <hi>The Lord turn the counſel of</hi> Achitophel <hi>into fooliſhneſs;</hi> which was ſo punctually anſwered, and that in ſo great a concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we cannot but take notice of prayer as having a chief hand in <hi>Davids</hi> Reſtauration. Prayer hath in like manner been made without ceaſing unto God for our <hi>David,</hi> and eſpecially in the zealous paſſion of many a Religious and Loyal heart; that God would in very termes <hi>turn the Counſel of</hi> Achitophel
<hi>into fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 35.9.</note> 
               <hi>By reaſon of oppreſsion they have made the people to cry, they have cried out by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Arm of the Mighty.</hi> When good men have ſeen how the wicked have proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, and how they have abuſed their ſucceſſes; made God the Patron and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettor of their villanies, and ſought themſelves all along to the ruine of true Religion; they have cryed to God with their voice, they have ordered their cauſe before God, filled their <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33913:21"/>mouthes with Arguments, pleaded Gods Covenant, their own integrity in the main, the reproach of Religion, the inſolency and rage of the enemy, and have waited
<note place="margin">Pſ 94.14,15.</note> 
               <hi>when God ſhould return judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto righteouſneſs, that the upright in heart might follow after it.</hi> This hath prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led much in our <hi>Davids</hi> caſe. When God ſaw
<note place="margin">2 Kings 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>there was none ſhut up, and none left in Iſrael,</hi> and yet his people cryed to him, his
<hi>own Arm hath brought ſalvation</hi> to his people. He hath looked down, from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven did the Lord behold the earth,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 79.10,11.</note> 
               <hi>to hear the groans of the priſoners, and to deliver thoſe that were appointed to dye.</hi> It appears that he <hi>hath ſeen, he hath ſeen</hi> all this while the affliction of <hi>his ſervant,</hi> and his people; theſe prayers have moved him to come down to deliver. As in a like caſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.23. They cryed by reaſon of their bondage, and their cry came up to God, and God hath remembred us, and had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto us. If men will adventure to abuſe any of Gods children, they had beſt do it out of the Fathers ſight (which is impoſſible) or to take heed they make them not <hi>cry;</hi> for if they cry God, will know the matter, and it will be hard with them that do them wrong. God will not alwayes endure his peoples cryes againſt any that oppreſs them. This was a <pb n="25" facs="tcp:33913:21"/>ſecond help, and notable means that kept <hi>Davids</hi> Affairs alive, the Spirit of Prayer, that lay continually at the Throne of Grace, moving the King of Heaven for aſſiſtance, to reſtore the baniſhed King to his Right again: And this was more than if the greateſt Potentates had joined by their Forces to ſet him in the Throne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>God did defeat their Counſels;</hi> he divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and defeated their Counſels: <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> gave counſel to do quickly what they did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. <hi>Huſhai</hi> gives advice to the contrary. <hi>Abſolom</hi> takes the wrong coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, <hi>ver.</hi> 14.
<hi>For the Lord had appointed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat the good counſel of Achitophel, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that he might bring evil upon Abſolom.</hi> This is the plain of the buſineſs, God ſpoils their Counſels, thereby to defeat and deſtroy their deſign. Whether the Lord hath had any <hi>Huſhai's</hi> in the Counſels that intended our <hi>Davids</hi> good, I know not; but God hath made ſome Counſels to ſerve well <hi>Davids</hi> turn; and the very like diſappointment of the deſign of the late formidable Army, in the very ſame kind, that they forthwith fell not upon the <hi>Renowned General who oppoſed them; that they would gather all Iſrael together for this purpoſe;</hi> or what it was, but God divided them in their party before, to work their ruine, Counſels divided, and Forces divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Many a thing, no doubt, that party<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33913:22"/>can now ſay, may have been on foot, which if taken, had prevented their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw; but God hath done all this, to the intent that he <hi>might bring evil on our Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loms,</hi> and their trayterous Deſign.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>God removes one dangerous Inſtrument after another, out of Davids way. Achitophel</hi> hangs himſelf, <hi>Abſoloms</hi> Army is defeated in a bloody Battel, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.8. <hi>The Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel was ſcattered all over the Countrey, and the Wood devoured more people that day, then the ſword devoured. Abſolom</hi> himſelf is found and ſlain, hanging in an Oak; the great Heads and Ring-leaders of the Faction being removed thus by the hand of God, way is notably prepared for <hi>Davids</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. God hath wrought as wonderfully in the like manner to remove the prime Uſurpers, to make way for the Kings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s gone, and
<hi>Abſolom</hi>'s gone; and though God hath mightily ſaved from the effuſion of blood, yet he hath by a wonderful hand diſperſed and broken a potent and terrible Army, even <hi>without hands,</hi> in the late Northern defeat; God knows <hi>what wood they fell into,</hi> but there were they broken,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.4.</note> 
               <hi>there are the ſtout-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fallen, they have ſlept their ſleep, and none of the men of might have found their hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>God ſtirs up the people generally to think and take counſel to bring the King back.</hi> They fall to conſultation about it, 2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 19.9,10 <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33913:22"/>Two things they mention to move one another to return to <hi>their Loyalty,</hi> and to endeavour the reſtoring
<hi>David</hi> to his Right. 1. They remember the relation he had ſtood in unto them, the good works he had done, what a Deliverer he had been as an Inſtrument in Gods hand unto them, 2. They take notice, that
<hi>Abſolom</hi> that was the Competitor, whom they had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, was dead in the Battel; &amp; therefore there remained nothing more reaſonable for them, then that they ſhould ſpeak of <hi>bringing the King back.</hi> The people were ſtrangely turned of late in their hearts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our
<hi>David;</hi> they begin now to cal the King to mind again, that had bin forgotten all this while, ſome years, and ſcarce ſo much as named. And there was two things that very much ſwayed with ſome men, to think that God pointed at the King's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration; 1. The miraculous preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the King, that he was ſo delivered and eſcaped, when his life was ſought as he was. 2. That that deſperate Uſurper and Competitor was ſo ſtrangely removed out of the way. It was not long ſince a great piece of Diſcourſe, That if we muſt have Monarchy, there muſt be a continued competition between the two Lines of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> and the <hi>Cromwells;</hi> this latter having ſetled himſelf as firmly, as the wickedeſt Wit and Policy of man could contrive; and<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33913:23"/>yet God daſhed all this by Creatures of his own, by contrary Factions, he and his ſettlement is removed as eaſily, as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be eſtabliſhed firmly: They that pulled that Line down, little intending to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ake way for the lawful Soveraign.
<hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom</hi> that would have a Pillar to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by, in the Kings Dale,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.18.</note> exchanges it or an ignominious heap of ſtones in the Wood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Our Uſurper is not left to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignomious and odious to him whom he had wronged, but his own faction do this to our hand, his Pillar pulled up,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial in a years time is periſhed with him.</hi> And hence the people might well conſult to ſtir for their Liberties, and to ſee by theſe many weary toſſings and changes, they were out of the way, and under the Lords curſe for their Rebellions, and Treacheries, and Diſloyalties, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might well ſee that their hope of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement muſt needs be in <hi>bringing the King back</hi> God preſerved him ſure, and not for nothing. God hath ſo removed <hi>Abſolom,</hi> that it directs the whole People to look after
<hi>David,</hi> and the Elders of all the Tribes ſeaſonably to declare for a free Convention, their undoubted Right, which the Adverſaries all along interpreted to be as much as to reſolve to bring <hi>the King back.</hi> And ſo upon the meeting of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33913:23"/>in Parliament, they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved after a day of ſolemn Humiliation, on
<hi>Tueſday, May</hi> 1. to conſider expreſly of this matter.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>While the people are conſidering to bring the King back,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.11,12. <hi>David ſends to Zadock and Abiathar and the Elders of Judah, and to Amaſa the General, his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and Declaration, whereby he incites and encourages them to fetch him back. How like is this to his Majeſties Letters and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Parliament, to the General, and to the City,</hi> expreſſing himſelf ſo affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them, <hi>as bone of their bone, and fleſh of their fleſh,</hi> as he doth; offering not onely Pardon, but Preferment to ſuch as ſhould ſeaſonably return to their Loyalty and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. This helped <hi>Davids</hi> Affairs very much.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>The effect of Davids Meſſage and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, was,</hi> That the Prieſts, the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the General, they all are affected with it, and return an unanimous and cordial Anſwer to <hi>David,</hi> and invite him to return with all his Servants: This is juſt our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent poſture, the <hi>heart of all the people is bowed as the heart of one man.</hi> Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are now ſent to his Majeſty, of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Land, both Lords and Commons, from the General, of the Miniſters, all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting moſt affectionately his Majeſties Grace and Favour, and particularly invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33913:24"/>him, nay with ſpeed to return unto his People.</p>
            <p>This is the preſent poſture of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: I ſhall follow the parallel no further, ſince we are yet brought but thus far, though we humbly hope and expect the joyful Return of the King to his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Royal City; but that God hath brought things thus far, we are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Authority to keep this ſolemn Day of Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p>Thus we have conſidered the manner how God hath brought
<hi>Davids</hi> re-ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to paſs:</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi>dly.</hi> Let us conſider the greatneſs <hi>of the thing which the Lord hath thus effected,</hi> which may truly further us in the great duty of the day. It is a wonderful worke.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we conſider <hi>what a change it wrought,</hi> how far things were gone another way, and how God hath reduced them quite back again; <hi>David</hi> under this invitation from all his people, <hi>to return back with all his ſervants,</hi> when a little before looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>as the common Enemy,</hi> and all with him perſecuted as <hi>Traytors;</hi> a little before the people ready to ſay, <hi>We have no Portion in the ſon of Jeſſe; Let David looke to his own Houſe. Charles Stuart</hi> was the beſt Title our Sovereign could have; the Son of the late Tyrant, the curſed Intereſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now it is <hi>our Soveraign Lord the King, with<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33913:24"/>all his Titles;</hi> and every one ſtrives who ſhall have the greateſt ſhare in him: Men are now ſtriving who ſhall be <hi>firſt</hi> to bring the King back. Compare two places or Scripture in this ſtory, and you will ſay there is a great and wonderful change wrought
2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.6,7,8. &amp; 19 19,20. the very <hi>Shimei,</hi> the ſame man ſpeaks both thoſe ſpeeches. It was even now, <hi>Go up thou bloody man,</hi> God hath now reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned with thee; <hi>I</hi> know not what blood is laid at <hi>Davids</hi> door. As it is eaſie to find matter in the beſt mans life for an uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable cenſurer to aſcribe his troubles unto; if a man be greatly afflicted, he muſt be greatly in fault in the worlds eyes: But now his very <hi>Shimei</hi> deſires pardon; and therefore he is the firſt of all the Houſe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> that comes to meet the King: Would one ever have a thought that this very man ſhould a few weeks ſince have bin throwing ſtones at <hi>David,</hi> and caſting duſt in the ayre, and curſing him. What a worke is this, the people that ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this
<hi>Moſes,</hi> now receive him loyally and cordially? The <hi>Shimei</hi>'s that curſed him, now are ready to go firſt out to meet him. The very ſame
<hi>Barbarians</hi> that count <hi>Paul</hi> a Murderer when the Viper's on his hand, have much ado to with-hold ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice from him as a God, when they ſee the Viper ſhaken off into the Fire, and <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33913:25"/>he unhurt. What hath the Lord wrought? When now we have command &amp; authority to pray for the King, which a few Months ſince ſhould have been accounted Treaſon.
<note place="margin">Prov. 11.8</note> 
               <hi>The Righteous are delivered out of trouble, and the wicked are come in their ſtead.</hi> This is a wonderful change, a mighty work that is wrought.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this is brought to paſs <hi>ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly</hi> and <hi>unexpectedly.</hi> God hath done for us
<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.3.</note> 
               <hi>things we looked not for;</hi> It is the Lord that hath thus ſubdued <hi>David</hi>'s People under him; That they which drove him out, or durſt not appear to call him in, ſhould now all unanimouſly appear; and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as it were one ſoul ſhould poſſeſs all the people, and they ſhould joyn to call the King back.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.47. &amp; 114 3.</note> 
               <hi>It is the Lord that ſubdues my People under me,</hi> ſaid <hi>David:</hi> As it was ſaid of the change of Religion in <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>'s time:
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 29.30.</note> God <hi>had prepared the heart of the People, for the thing was done ſuddenly.</hi> The Houſe may ſoon be reared, when all the Materials are prepared and made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and framed to ſetting up; The Lord laid this buſineſs in his own counſel, he fitted the heart of the people to concur in the Fundamentall Conſtitutions of the Nation, as the onely means of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, opened almoſt all mens eyes to ſee the hypocriſie, ſelfiſhneſs, tyranny and falſity of thoſe that had thus long abuſed<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33913:25"/>us. And ſo the work upon this opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is done ſuddenly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That God hath therein ſo much vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Religion, and his own glory.</hi> One great thing that troubled <hi>David</hi> in his flight from <hi>Abſolom,</hi> was, That his Enemies dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, <hi>There was no help for him in his God, Pſal.</hi> 3.2. A Pſalm penned upon this very occaſion; and this troubled him more then any thing; it was like
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.10</note> 
               <hi>a Sword in his Bones, while the Enemy still ſaid, Where is now thy God?</hi> Oh how oft was God's people run through with this reproach? How were they mocked with their prayers? How was God's Providence blaſphemed? How did the Enemies brag that they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten God to their ſide,
<note place="margin">2 Kings 18 25</note> 
               <hi>and that they were not come up without God againſt us?</hi> But the Lord made the Enemies know, that
<hi>David</hi> was not forgotten, he works now the other way, for ever to ſilence the Enemy about Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. When was ever ſuch a work wrought in al they have blaſphemouſly bragg'd for them, as God hath now wrought againſt them? Thoſe wretched Gyants, that would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they build by his allowance, becauſe they had his permiſſion; he hath now at once come down and confounded their Language, and ſpoil'd their <hi>Babel</hi> in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; It may be now ſaid,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 58.11</note> 
               <hi>Verily there is a Reward for the Righteous.</hi> Verily hee is <hi>a God</hi> that judgeth in the Earth: We can<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33913:26"/>ſhew the Phanatique now, where our God is.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi>ly.</hi> The <hi>work</hi> is wonderful, <hi>in that ſuch way is made for a perfect ſettlement.</hi> Trees ſhaken by the Wind, take Root the faſter. <hi>David</hi> is not onely brought back to the Throne, but no doubt it is ſetled faſter than ever, by the late convulſion upon it. We may conceive, the people ſeeing the <hi>premunire</hi> the ambitious Uſurpers had led them into, the loſs they had ſuſtained by it, the danger they were in, if they might now have the King's favour, would be more firm to him then ever they were, and more wary of hearkening to Uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers while they lived. The King alſo might ſee ſomewhat that
<hi>Abſolom</hi> might catch, to make a grievance of, for the people, that they ſhould thereupon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oin in commotion againſt him; and ſo might remove that prejudice, and ſee to the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, to prevent the like diſcontent for the time to come. They have liberty, ſeveral of them, to ſhew their good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in bringing him back, and ſo to have pardon, upon which they might be firmly engaged to him, and ſo the ſtate more happy in King and People for ever after; as it appears, one <hi>Sheba</hi> after made a ſlight Rebellion, but few followed him, and as eaſily it was quelled. No ſuch cure of a Nations diſcontents, as when people find<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33913:26"/>that patience is better then any remedies of their own that can be applyed. I ſhall not here ſpeak of things that have paſſed in this Nation theſe laſt twenty years, (for I am but of yeſterday) ſad breaches have been between Prince and People, King and Parliament. God hath ſadly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted both, and I hope pardoned both: Why ſhould we now go about to lay the fault at either door, when God ſeems to be in a way of forgiveneſs of it? And ſure the Lord hath put ſuch an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity into our hands of a perfect ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as we have not had before; <hi>Dulce eſt bellum inexpertis:</hi> Sure God hath taught us for being forward in drawing the Sword again in haſt. O a deſperate reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it is! and eſpecially when this is well conſidered, that there was an Enemy that was lately in Power, would have made no difference between any ſober men of each party in the Nation; God having joined us in the deliverance, cannot we keep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether after it? Why ſhould not the old enmity be laid aſide? God hath underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and anſwered the honeſt deſires of all: What the Allegiance and Conſcience of Duty obligeth ſome unto, that the ſame Principles, and the Covenant in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner oblige others unto: You are for the King's juſt Rights, we are for the ſame; Why then ſhould we not be all one? Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33913:27"/>when his <hi>Majeſty</hi> doth uſe ſuch pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical terms in his own Declarations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now read unto us, to <hi>command, invite, and coniure us to lay aſide all animoſities, &amp;c.</hi> as he doth; we are agreed at preſent, or may be if we will; And have we not had enough of the old quarrel? If either obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God or the King ſway with us, we muſt lay down our ſinful and uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable diſtances, and be united, as God hath united us in this great mercy which he hath granted to us all, to make us friends. We may allude to that of
<hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſh</hi> to <hi>Amaziah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 14.9</note> We had beſt thiſtles fight with Cedars, and one with another, till God find another wild beaſt to eat up the <hi>Thiſtle.</hi> Hath God found out our <hi>Joſeph</hi> for us, and ſhall we now fall out by the way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the guilt of his looſing? There is great hopes of a perfect ſettlement, when God hath thus ſuffered us to tyre our ſelves in our confuſions and diviſions theſe many years—And theſe Conſiderations makes this a great occaſion of our rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing before God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome may object upon this; <hi>We fear what may be the iſſue of this change, we may happen run into another extream; we alwayes feared Religion might be more hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Change, then it was before, &amp;c. and therefore we are much afraid in this day of our rejoicing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33913:27"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer to this very briefly:</p>
            <p n="1">1. I hope that thoſe that truly fear God, do as dearly fear the things of God and Religion upon their hearts, as ever they did; and as in the Day of their trouble, when God ſmote them into the place of Dragons, they were able to ſay in ſome meaſure of ſincerity and humble confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.17</note> 
               <hi>All this is come upon us, yet have we not forgotten thee, neither have dealt falſly in thy Covenant.</hi> So in this day when God turned again their Captivity, they are as ready to ſay, <hi>If I forget thee, O Jeruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning; If I do not remember thee, let my Tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth, if I prefer not Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem above my chief joy.</hi> I do hope we are not ſo far tranſported with our occaſions of rejoicing, as to forget Religion as our chiefeſt concernment.</p>
            <p n="2">But ſecondly, It were worth our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, how much this pretence <hi>of ſecuring Religion</hi> hath miſcarried of late times; We have ſecured <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſee what it hath effected.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Liberty for the bad, as well as the good: It is a queſtion not abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, whether is the better, to have the bad abſolutely ſuppreſſed, though the good thereby be afflicted too; or, to have the good have their utmoſt liberty, and the bad and unfound have as much liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33913:28"/>as they; God can order things be ſides both extreams: Yet I believe the ſufferings of good men never hurt the Church ſo, as the Liberty of bad men hath done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Where hath our encreaſe been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our late proſperity?
<note place="margin">Prov. 29.1</note> The <hi>Churches had reſt,</hi> and <hi>they multiplyed,</hi> and were <hi>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;</hi> And ſure if our reſt had been in God's Way, we might have ſeen it more bleſſed unto us. There hath been little encreaſe, few converted under means.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We have ſecured Religion, but ſeem many Apoſtates from it, as ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one Age brough forth, even in this little while. The damnable monſtrous Doctrines that have been vended; thoſe evils are gotten into the Church in this time of Liberty, that it is well if any thing but ſome perſecution or fiery try<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al may expel.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The love of many is waxed cold; zeal and heat in godlineſs is loſt from them that retain the ſound Doctrine; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is gotten a politick thing with a great many, a Sceleton, an outſide, the power of it loſt in a great meaſure, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this glorious talk of Religion.</p>
            <p n="5">And fifthly, We have gotten ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon it in theſe late yeares, by that which we have done under the higheſt profeſſion of it, that hath been<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33913:28"/>the greateſt diſhonour to Chriſt, ſince his Church hath been upon earth, I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve. And if Religious men ſhould be under contempt, for what hath been done by falſe Profeſſors of it, it cannot be worſe then may well be looked for, and it is well known who may be thanked for it,
<note place="margin">Mat 18.7</note> 
               <hi>Woe to them by whom theſe offences come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſecuring Religion hitherto me thinks hath looked like reſt that a man ſick is forced to, he is quiet with it, or ſeems to reſt quietly, but when he awakes, he profeſſes he is not refreſhed at all by it. And ſo what ever you can fear, it is not worſe then the beſt in effect that hath bin: our reſt hath not been kindely, hath not come in wayes that God hath bleſſed; and ſo not done us that good which might have been expected.</p>
            <p n="3">And thirdly, It will be a great while in likelihood before things on another hand to ſuch an height, as to make our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion comparably hazardous to what it lately was. Is their danger of deſtroying the Miniſtry, pulling up the Univerſities, ſhutting up the Church doors, &amp;c. All which, and much more you are juſt eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from?</p>
            <p n="4">Fourthly, As far as Religion can be ſecured <hi>in Gods way,</hi> we are to look to it, and to make it our care. But when we muſt uſe extraordinary extravagant cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33913:29"/>to ſettle it, I beleeve we ſhall have no thanks for it, as the Apoſtle with deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion expreſſes it. As <hi>we be ſlanderouſly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported,
<note place="margin">Rom 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Let us do evil that good may come of it, whoſe damnation is juſt.—</hi> Further then we can ſecure Religion in Gods way, it ceaſeth to be our duty or care. We diſtruſt Gods All-ſufficiency, when we will offer to do his work by the Devils means. It was an excellent Monition that <hi>Luther</hi> gave to
<hi>Melancthon,</hi> when he was over ſollicitous, about what ſhould become of the Church when things looked darkly towards it; ſayes he in a Letter to his neighbour Miniſters, <hi>Monendus eſt per nos Philippus, ut deſinat eſſe Rector mundi: Philip</hi> is to be admoniſhed by you that he ceaſe uſurping to be the Ruler of the world. So I could wiſh we would take more care of duty, and leave the iſſue and ſucceſs of all things unto God. Let the Government of the Church lye on his ſhoulders on which God hath laid it, who will take care of it when thou and I are in our graves, eſpecially commands thee to lay thy hands off this care, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then thy plain duty appears unto thee in it.</p>
            <p n="5">Fifthly, What if ſufferings ſhould come? Why 1. We ſuffered before. 2. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings muſt not come unleſs <hi>(need be)</hi> and nothing ſhall come but what is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33913:29"/>but what is in the Phiſicians Bill to do the Patient good with. 3: We ſhall have peace of conſcience in our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that we have not by unrighteous means ſought to prevent them.</p>
            <p n="6">But ſixthly, Why ſhould we count it neceſſary that the Church muſt fare the worſe for this change? Is it any thing leſs than a limiting the holy One of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> when he hath brought us out of
<hi>Egypt</hi> by a mighty hand as he hath done, to be queſtioning already, whether he
<note place="margin">Pſ. 78.19,20.</note> 
               <hi>can provide a Table for us in the Wilderneſs.</hi> To receive ſuch a wonderful mercy from God ſo unexpectedly, and ſo undeſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and at the very next turn to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting and counting of the very worſt, is not ſo reaſonable; why may we not hope, that the ſame Almighty power and free mercy will not perfect the work, that hath begun it? God hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed better credit at our hands by his late works then this comes to.</p>
            <p>And what ſhould all the hopes which God gives in his inſtrument, the <hi>David</hi> in the occaſion ſtand for nothing with us! may not the Lord vindicate Religious Loyalty in his <hi>Majeſties eyes? The heart of the King is in the hand of the Lord, and he can turn it as the Rivers of water.</hi> He can do by it as the Husbandman by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, makes it overflow what fields he<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33913:30"/>pleaſes to his advantage, can drain or drown what place he will with it, ſo can God turn the heart of the King. Why ſhould it be doubted but that it may be evidenced, that many have deteſted the horrid villanies that have been perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated in the late confuſions, have mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuffered under them? And why ſhould it but be hoped that a Prince of ſuch ſufferings, deliverances, prayers, and experiences, but that God hath a large in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in his heart?
<note place="margin">Acts 19.32</note> 
               <hi>And when the Righteous are in Authority, the people may rejoyce.</hi> And therefore I do conceive that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Objections that men of diſcontented, peeviſh (and many of them guilty) ſpirits, can ſuggeſt of fears; we are not excuſable from ſerious and ſolid rejoycing in our God upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall from all infer two or three things in way of uſe, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us learn hence the mighty power of God. What cannot the Lord do? What deſperate ſtate of affairs cannot he put life into? How far was <hi>Davids</hi> affairs gone, and yet now he is invited back to his Throne. He can alter things as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. He can make the people that durſt ſcarce name him, unanimouſly ſend for him. He can bow the hearts of Kings and people to accord and ſit down to<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33913:30"/>gether. Truly God hath done that in this little while we could not have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. He hath turned our Captivity like <hi>the ſtreams in the South,</hi> and we are ſtil like
<note place="margin">Pſal. 126 1</note> 
               <hi>men that dream.</hi> We were inured to the Pots &amp; Brick-kilns, to the ſervice wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our Maſters made us to ſerve with ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and we counted ſtill of it, but God hath changed the ſtate with us, and that on a ſudden, who would have ſaid that we that durſt ſcarce keep a day of Faſting to ovvn our affliction, ſhould have kept one day after another in vvay of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for our Deliverances. It is the Lords doing, and a mighty God is he.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Learn hence the profit and ſafety of honeſt and direct dealing; this fears no after-claps, or after-reckonings. The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous now are bold as a Lion.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Wilt thou not be afraid of the power, do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame.</hi> If there be no unrighteouſneſs in thy hand, thou needeſt not fear an inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into former things.
<note place="margin">Prov. 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>He that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth uprightly, walketh ſurely.</hi> A good cauſe it ſeems can never be buried. God will bring forth the integrity of his ſervants, and make a difference even in this world, betvven them that have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly cleaved cloſe to him, and them that have turned aſide to crooked paths.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33913:31"/>3. Keep your hearts ſtill up to God, notwithſtanding what God hath done for you. It is not God hath ſaved you thus far, and the Kings that can ſave you out of the reſt. If God put us over to any mans ſalvation, we ſhall fall back into as bad or worſe then we were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Wait therefore on God, and let your expectation be from him, and ſtudy to keep ſo in with him, that he may pleaſe to perfect what he hath begun.</p>
            <p>And to this end, Labour eſpecially to rejoyce like Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let not your National mercies make you forget your perſonal intereſt and buſineſs. Look to the ſoul as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly now as at any time, do not think that God gets you leave to play, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſecret ſeriouſneſs by his great mercies vouchſafed to you. Beware you loſe not your hearts from God and Religion, in reſpect of inward ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret duties by theſe providences. For firſt, you will miſs of the beſt part of your comfort if you neglect God, in, and beſides theſe mercies. Theſe things are not able to ſatisfie your ſouls, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs an inward intereſt be ſecured and made under them. Secondly, You are ſubject to particular croſſes under this general joy. If your joy take you off your duty, a croſs may ſoon come which<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33913:31"/>may take you off your joy. Thirdly, You muſt dye, and this will be little to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that, and no part of your time can be ſpared from preparing for that change. Nay you may dye in the midſt of theſe joyful dayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.22,23. <hi>When the people are gathered together, and the Kingdomes to ſerve the Lord, he weakened my ſtrength; in the way he ſhortened my dayes,</hi> and therefore it is good to minde the ſoul, what ever your joy in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Diſhonour not God, in the day, or upon occaſion of your rejoycing: you pretend to honour God, do not under ſuch a pretence do ſacrifice to Sathan: And I muſt needs here ſpeak of a prophane and wicked practice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to break out, and upon this mercy too. (The worſt time that can be for ſin to meet ſo eminent a mercy in, leſt it ſhould turn it back again) and that is, that men fall a drinking <hi>of healths,</hi> as if you could not teſtifie your affection to your King, unleſs you do apparent diſhonour unto God; for men to make this an Engine to intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and exceſs in drunkenning, it is very unworthy and unbecoming. It is that which an Heathen King forbad, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1.8. His Majeſty we hear, meaſures the affections of his Subjects by the Prayers<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33913:32"/>they put for him, and not by the healths they drink unto him; and I hope ſuch as theſe that are a diſhonour to God, and the King too, will in time be made to know it; <hi>Hath the Lord given us ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance as this, and ſhall we again break his holy Commandments?</hi> Was this all the burthen that lay upon us, that we had not liberty to drink, and revel, or to blaſpheme? Or is this the way to have this mercy continued or compleated? O lay aſide this wretched Exceſs, out of obedience to God, and the King too; For be you well aſſured, theſe courſes will ſoon breed new Judgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; he that hath cauſed it <hi>towards Evening to be light, can make our Sun to ſet at noon.</hi> Labour to be Chriſtians ſtill, and to carry like Chriſtians under this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull mercy, for the Chriſtian hath not had the leaſt hand in the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:32"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33913:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
